Everyone it's three thirty in the afternoon most you guys probably have a lot of fun last night we know we had a few
...please stand-up.
...if you can.
Good afternoon everybody.
That's better...
...see we're going to have a lot of fun today all right
so john sheehan and I'm going to be talking about project centennial and,
I guess remember submit your valuations told us that.
...well first of all who...right so why not why my appear
talk to-you my name's john chien I've been on the windows team for five or
six years I think and I came into windows during windows eight to do the windows
...model which now is we...the universal windows
app platform something ...keeps getting renamed I can't keep up.
So, actually came to microsoft from a company called softer city
who microsoft acquired so how many people know softer city...a product called soft grid how many have heard of
Few more at v was this really cool or is this really cool product
...enterprises use
to virtual lies their software and people always wondered what
...that...and we're going to talk about those kind of things today but, yeah, so,
now I basically I work on the ...work in the developer
platform team doing stuff like I do the app model in some other things but,
anyway, so, let's we talking about today by the way personal
...disclaimer for-you this project is still under development
first that means that it's not in the bits that you're getting today so all the stuff
you see on stage here today you won't be able to do in your builds it will come...some future
flight of windows and, also I'm working with...bits that were compiled on
...machine like the other day so you probably?
Might run into a couple issues if we do just...clapping we'll get through it.
So, what is project centennial is a bridge
from the allow you to convert your classic windows apps to universal
...and it's probably one of the coolest things I think we've done
...a long-time because it's actually?
As I'll take you through today you'll see it's almost magical it is very similar to what we did with
that v which is basically allow you to take an application that
was written like...those kind of things and actually convert it to be and app
...app...through the store...all those things so it's very cool
so what's beget so why do we do project see and for the rest of this thing
...just obviously way too long first of all there is a huge ecosystem
of classic windows apps out there I think I...in the keynote...on...we have like
sixteen million classic windows apps your when thirty-two your dot net apps your
...formats and we obviously
knew that all these developers wanted to be on the latest platform they wanted to use all the latest
features and they had a huge investment in their code but, you know,
with the universal windows that model there was really know great path for them I mean
it was basically the story was great rewrite your app
you'll be fine and that's is obviously a terrible story?
So, we heard we heard the feedback how about that we heard the feedback so, we started looking at
what would it look like to really embrace these apps and bring them forward and bring their code
forward and all the cool things that they do ford.
And, the first thing we ran into was basically the issue that.
For windows for when thirty-two...apps there's no such thing as
...app but there's no definition of it this was my big...this is the thing that accidentally got me into windows for me
just yelling at the windows team saying you don't have an app model
...app and you just can't do it it's like well it's we have pe files like...exes in
the dls so we...files on disks we have registry entries we have
and si files but the moment that those things get put on the system.
It's just staff the os doesn't understand anything about it and
...really can't do anything to help keep the system
...update the applications on install the application
nothing so when we did in windows eight when we did the windows
...that model we knew that we needed to have a very clean-up model that
apps could very easily be deployed they wouldn't harm the system how many of ever installed
...msi and your system was never...ever again.
There...right so that was one of the issues that we had when we started looking at, you know,
taking these classic windows apps...forward and really
when we talked about it people always said we really want to...
...huge feedback from developers saying I have a great app why can I sell
...in the store and we had the well,
you can put a link to your website in the store and no one was very happy with that because
it means you couldn't use...payment methods you couldn't use anything so.
First we needed that model and we had two options we could create a new
...model yet another one or we could just use the one that we already have for
universal windows apps and just bring classic windows apps into that.
So, we basically decided for the latter obviously and
...the other really cool thing about the approach that we're taking is that you can start
...just do a conversion process and your app x you can be in the store
you're set and then over time you can start to change or you can start to evolve
it you can start to move more things into the you know, into the app container into the universal
...platform and at a certain point you won't have any the
...classic stuff left anymore and now you run everywhere so it's
really cool story we're going to talk a lot about that today and,
the end result is going to be a really great user experience right I mean
devote users for classic windows apps are used to this download
nemesis I double-click on it get a welcome window that just says hey you're about to install something
hit next now it starts asking you questions about installing the something...hit next again the
next again then you wait thirty minutes because it's doing something-or-other god knows what
and then when you're done hopefully your system still works right that's the old experience?
No, experience is the same exact experience of people get when they use when they do
you ws which is I go to store or I can side
...from side loading and I hit a button undone but the app installs
...progress when the installs done I have I have shortcuts and tiles and I can launch them
and things work and, another really cool thing about it is because
these are just regular apps now you get all the same auto update experience
and everything three o'clock in the morning system wakes up checks for updates if
...it pulls them down and, you know, and, they're,
you know, they get installed and...you get things like all of the great differing stuff that we do you
have a to gig package but you've only changed...of files...of all any
files have been change would never download because we already have them even ones that have changed
if they've only somewhat change we might we still might be able download part of the file and we do all that
adam automatically you don't have to do anything really,
really great user experience and, then the other thing is this concept of confidence
when we started windows eight we always talked about confidence which is, you know,
if...afraid.
To install your app what's the likelihood you're going to get their money while.
Is less than it would be if they weren't afraid right that fear of installing something
...install something I may have to re I've may have to re image my system
like that fear just doesn't help anybody so we really want to make sure as part
of this process that users can feel confident that they can try
...if they like it great they'll give you money they'll do whatever and if not
...and install it and also confident that the app is gone away and their system didn't slowly
So, that's really the experience that we're going for so what is the process look like for
project see pretty simple we have this tool or we will have this
to looks again I said this is still under development but,
you basically take your existing installer you
run it one last time and you do it witnessed with the tool running that basically sits there and the
kernel just catches everything bundles adopt turns into
an app x and you're good.
All you have to do that point is obviously just tester app just like any other time you change something
and, at that point you're ready you can...to the store from that point ford you should be able to
just in visual studio generate those packages directly and never even have to go back to and
msi ever get unless you need to support windows
seven or other releases in which case you'll still have to keep your msi around but,
at least you should be able to have a single binary that will run on seven
installed...msi and then ten, you know, installed using affects.
All right so talking great.
But, I think probably rather see something so let's do let's start looking at map and look at what this looks
And, in the keynote use that they launched.
Adobe photoshop elements thirty and you know, we
kinda did it really quickly so you can see what was happening but this version of
adobe photoshop elements we just ran through this tool.
we took their msi installer we ran it through the tool and
at first it didn't quite work and the only thing that didn't work and this is from all
my years experience that v is always the same thing it's licensing right
...your app relies on the fact that...installer, you know,
as part of installation goes and looks at the system
...like says all right what's the serial number of the cpu if I can get that let
me go see what hard-drive they have...what size and basically looks...the network card
...at a bunch of stuff it takes these measurements of your system of the user system
packages all up and in some encrypted format does all this crazy stuff so that people want
...your software and of course with this technique what do we do we go on one machine we
run the install package...all up...to another machine and of course the install
code the licensing code falls over...so the adobe...very quickly just
...great they gave us another they gave us another si this one...turn their licensing stuff off.
...through the tool and this is literally the version like we read...just...and we were
dot so it was very easy now that being
said as I talk about the technical details later it's not always that easy you
may have to changer code...your code may be doing things that don't work
well project centennial brought a lot of them but they're definitely some and but,
luckily if you fix those things that code will also continue to work on, you know,
windows seven windows a windows eight one so the code
and the binary will continue to work the same it's just that it might have to do
something slightly different right so let's quickly let's look at...elements.
So, we go in here launches it using the network which is always a
...job all right so, this is adobe elements and
as you can see as I said things can go wrong and always do and look at my task
bars gone which is good as I said this is literally a
build of windows we took off one of our machines so,
but, as long as all tab still works on find will be fine all
right so let's first go look and see what happens so if I go in here and look
at the photoshop elements you'll actually see the command-line that was
run and you can see it's under program files windows apps
blah-blah-blah bunch of other stuff by the way some of these perhaps a really long and
they've got a bunch of goods and stuff that is just an artifact of like where we're at the
project will finally be like that
will be much cleaner we are for the prototype we are standing up and using at v.
To help stand-up but this is not app v is actually one of the things I wanted
to make abundantly clear in this talk is that.
While a...the same techniques about
...v it has a very different goal...v
...to enterprises, enterprises receive microsoft size and then at
that point the enterprise was responsible for doing conversion getting the app working and running
and enterprise doesn't even have access to that code like adobe doesn't give,
you know, enterprises the
bits I'm sorry the cplus-plus code for photoshop they give them the binary
...so they really had no opportunity to ever change any
of the code so because of that...v has to do
like really unnatural things like the kinds of things that hey I know it looks
like a bug but the apps relying on the bug so like it needs to be bug for
...compatible with anything that happens in windows we don't have to do that right
so we're, you know, you are target audience your the developer gr
aperture code if you have a bug in your code.
Just go fix it.
Like I do I fix...bug in the...like, you know, we have bugs...code...fix so if...your code please
...go fix it if you're doing something you're not supposed to like some was asking well, you know,
I'm using the registry as like a job q and there's different processes
...out and I'm like well.
Actually that would work but please stop doing that like it's
a configuration database it's not your job q...file like that's...files before so,
you will have to make some code changes I guarantee it but it won't be a lot and again once you
make those changes those will still continue to work on previous versions of windows cb fine
so if we look here we have this thing is it has been
installed the owners I do the install by the way is a to gig package so it takes like a
minute-and-a-half or something install and you just don't want to sit there and watch install needed iso but,
I just installed it with the regular...app x package commands.
Did install and it obviously put it under windows apps because that's where app
...apps go so we've got nap running with some ridiculously long
path and it's the photoshop elements editor so,
that's actually the version developments that's running...down now...
no explore this is a very immersive experience the shell so in my build?
So, let's first of all stuck.
See that...maximized that also.
Yes, we did a bunch of work on the command prompt by the way and regardless of all this other crazy stuff that we did we
get so much positive feedback on just thank you for finally fixing the command prompt sorta
...so we take a quick look here I'm in the I'm in the install directory,
directory for photoshop elements and you look at it if you've ever belts
metro sorry metro style lab universal windows app any of those things this will
are very familiar is going to block map because that's how we do that differential
streaming of the bits down during install it has an...manifest...supposed to have
...epics manifests because it's...app it has the metadata
...has the signature I mean it has all the stuff that is an app...out from
there's one other thing here too that you're going to see that we'll talk about a bit but just keep
...that registry dot that because that's something that's kind of interesting that's but most
...apps don't have but first let's just take a look at the app x manifest.
By the rambo really quick because I'm expecting that there's going to be a lot of questions so I think I'm
...try to get as many as I can so there's the epics...looks just like any other app
...manifest with a couple of differences you'll see in
there that's referencing a project see name space.
And, you'll see that.
The entry point is actually the photoshop elements thirteen oop xthree.
That's actually a full trust app when we launched...doesn't go to
and app container it just runs as the user and runs like
a normally would except for the fact that it's basically it's running in this little
environment where we where we show at the additional files and registry entries of expects and,
you can see like it's basically it has
...file type associations stuff like that.
It has live tile you can see it actually has a live tile.
As we talk a little bit more you'll see that these things really are.
Even though they're running under project see they really are universal
...you can do just...a not just what you can actually anything you can do with the regular universal.
All right so that's the manifest so.
If you look in here under.
Crazy longview...crazy longwood.
...go in here so you'll see that there's this directory called via
...if you look in here.
There's all this stuff right so there's just a bunch of directories and...you know,
they're they have somewhat common names like system and system x eighty-six go
look under system.
You'll see that there's a whole bunch of dls their.
Write the see runtime and nfc god they still use of
see feel so bad for these people.
But, anyways so this is the.
What the installer put in the system thirty-two directory right because the
...I...want you have to go change all your code so that you say all
well we used to be
...system thirty-two now I have to go and figure out where it is
like when you're running it will still look like it's...system thirty-two we'll talk...bit and we just...you?
Sorry virtual...
Right which is why you say hey under system thirty-two is that crazy
nfc dl there were like yup here you go.
So, basically this is how the file system stuff works is your.
Installer basically just vomiting files all over the file system.
We capture all in package it up and we keep it with your app one thing this will fix
...ever heard of something called...hell.
Right...running with this version...see some other...gets install
that has a slightly newer version of them...that's probably way better and,
...rather app in all of sudden your app that worked yesterday doesn't work today thats detail
...this is prevents that from happening.
All right so let's go back...go back down a couple directory use
doo-doo crazy do increase good.
All right so let's go in here.
You can look quickly there's basically.
The other thing that's in here is things like assets and stuff some very cool things is the moment that you
...the conversion you now have a lifestyle and you can
it's a real-live tile you can update your live tile you can do everything you would normally do...the live
tile you can start using w and immediately all those kind of things.
But, there's this one other thing that's sitting here which is this is registry dot that file
let's go okay all right my immersive experience...all I mean do start are so
...have to do this way so let's
...let's actually go and take a look and see what that thing is.
So, if I go and load so first of all that registry dot that file is actually
a high if it's right here so if I open...given the we'll call it pst.
And, this is actually.
The higher the high file that the converter creative.
So, what it...basically just like your installer like through all those
files on-disk it also through a ton of stuff in the registry
and we don't want that stuff there does anyone
know why when you install lots and lots and lots of apps like your system get slower
...like boot slower because all that stuff that you guys
...the registry because we told you to by the way so it's a hundred-percent our fault we told
you to put their and of our features like com required to be there unless, you know,
...free commish known does?
So, we told you put there so you did exactly what we told you put it there but what happens
is that registry file grows and grows and grows and then every time we
...the system we have to load the whole thing.
And, then you also put stuff in each case you.
And, that grows and every time user logs and we have to load that so that's why
over time you're like god when I first got this machine...booted really quick I was one of
the selling points and now year later a year-and-a-half later it boots, you know,
it's like ten seconds slower...why is that it's just because more stuff getting piled in the
...loaded so we don't want that and,
I don't think users do either so anyways when the installer ran.
Just going to look at something.
There's one that's ensure organizer go look at the registry the installer
...all this stuff down now...no idea what this is obviously only the adobe
engineers know what this stuff is but they obviously must really,
really rely on max undoable operations and main page file mem
...right so that's those things are really important to that app but they're really not
important boot the system so we take all that stuff and we put into this...file.
And, a little bit I'll talk about how it all actually comes together at the end
but so far this is basically what the installer did your system.
Funnily enough when at the first got bought by
microsoft's...got a call very quickly from the ...it the sequel server
t ok server stuff where clients stuff.
Nt service thingy were apps
and they said can we use the sequence or which is the tool that the has I said,
yeah, why this...we have no idea what...installer does the system we want to figured out?
...really they said, yeah,
so, Inext time...I went in there we sequence it over and they were like just spellbound for
hours going through what it and it's just stuff that accumulate over-the-air some engineer
and build some feature fifteen years ago and then updated the emma sided for
more stuff in there and that code is been sitting there forever and the big problem
they had by the way was that some time sequel server just kind of stop working.
And, it turned out it was like installation issues of course because somehow or other the installed
...work right because...just terrible...
By the way I owner
...I'm allowed to say that like it's you're allowed to say that about my product...can.
All right so that's basically what it looks like
that's the real running code as of like a couple of days ago it will get better.
So, let's go back to the dec so what was going on there.
What we did was we took this msi right and we run it through this
tool which we're calling the converter because we're really good with names?
And, what that does is...monitors everything that you're that
you're installer does to the system all the awful terrible things that does to the system
it sits there and catches all them it's basically a bunch of...filter drivers sits there
and kept captures everything and then it turns around...creates
...app acts but as part of creating the app x it actually needs to figure out what all
the junk was because some of that stuff's important like
com write the fact that a bunch of registry keys and dls all
thrown down on the system that's a come objects and we need to figure that stuff
up because later when we deploy the application we want to be able to tell...that there's a
...object there we don't want to do is just have to say hey...
as a whole bunch of registry stuff over here too so now start...more places to try to find all the
...stuff want to be able to telecom listen...installing...here some
com objects, you know, and, now you can know about them and we're actually hopefully we'll be able to do without
putting anything else in the registry so that the...registers days really small?
So, once they basically do all the analysis and package you figure all-out then we
spit it out into and app xfiles so basically the app xfiles going to have
a very specific format for project centennial there's going to be that
reads dot that file that basically will hold all your registry stuff.
Will be that separate will be a separate folder that contains all of the
things?
That we need to...you about right so all those files that your installer,
you know, tried to put in system thirty-two like we just got a very simple format where you say
if a file is in that
...in a directory called system we know that's the system thirty-two directory so,
for some...you might not...want to use the converter obviously you might want to say, you know, what?
I have an msi or I know what the my installer supposed to do
if you do you can skip it you can just basically, you know, create the app...
format yourself and just do it using regular tools and not even go through the converter.
...actually pretty convenience and as sequel server team taught us most you don't even know
...installs actually due to our systems.
So, then the...thing you need to do it as I
talked before is really you need to test an update now.
The project centennial like really want to embrace your apps.
But, not everything that you're at does right I have this talk I get which is called
...thirty-two the good parts.
Insinuating there's also when thirty-two the not-so-good
parts when thirty-two the good parts are things that apps do
...things that you do...running is the user you're not running in the kernel
like that's supposed to be for driver stuff that's was before hardware stuff you're not running is
an nt service that's supposed to be for...stuff?
Right we really got this we really got it all mixed up with
when thirty-two in that kind of just let you do anything
whether not saying hey these kind of things are good things to do these kind of things
...not so much maybe if maybe if you're and anti-virus better should be doing that because that's like
system software we're really targeting the apps the
...that users like interact with an get value out of and,
We've already way I've already talked privately to some companies and they sort of said ok
...symbol y and here's the number one reason is you remember that little
spiel at the beginning about a great user experience I...have at work.
What...on...is it smart to say hey I'm...admin I hit a
button and now because I hit the button there's code running is the system?
Probably not right if you're if you're an enterprise I can tell you
...group
will say definitely not and had we done that the very first thing we would have had to do
would have been add a group policy to turn that off right so rather than do
that we said hey we want users to feel confident that the software is not going to destroy
their systems so you only get to run is the user.
If you like your code running elevated as admin like usc prop style
So, if you're softwares doing stuff like that that's going to be the real change that you're going to
have to deal with luckily when we talk to a lot of people we find out why do you even have
...service...running all the time it
runs local system why are you doing that the number one reason can anyone guess.
Although of data is exactly right because I need to check every night to figure out if there's
new software and...the user intel new install and everything well guess what
we don't need your stupid auto...anymore we have one.
So, just take that code and throw it away right and let us
did let us deal with that mundane stuff all right
and then when you're done you get to make money right you get to go up to the
store you get lots of users and you get to sell your software?
So, I won't talk one more thing about at...at this stage because this diagram
is basically verbatim if I was up here giving...talk so people have been asking about well
...the navigate...this project centennial thing
art explain that they're very difference but one thing that the app the team is going to do
is if you convert to project centennial they will make sure that they can run
deploy manager software and potentially
even windows set now you...developers you probably don't
realize this but the ip groups in the enterprises that you sell your software
to they've they absolutely hate your installer...they hate them so much like
...they...awake at night thinking about them a lot of them spend a lot of money...convert that
v and if you can offer them packages that they don't have to take your installer
...once them and re convert them they're going to be really excited you will have some really,
really happy customers so the...teams...has committed to go off
...this work and...is really not that much work
...these two things are very similar but they're going to do that work so,
if you end up having a project see package you're going to be app be ready.
So, I'll talk a little bit about lying.
Sorry virtualization.
Most people ask how does the you know-how does all this stuff work what do I get to change what
do I see and it's actually pretty simple we do a
bunch of registry and file system merging and we do some re direction so
basically this is kind of what name space merging looks like your app actually
...emerge view of the world in
...everything on the local system so if there are, you know,
if there are...installed that you can load like you'll see all those you'll see all the
stuff that's normally on the system but then what will also do is we'll take that like those
see run-time or whatever all those files and we merge them in
and we create this merge view?
So, as far as your apps concerned the installer went off and made all kinds of changes to the system
because it looks exactly as if that happened but it really did one nice thing
about this is first of all we don't money up the system...up with dl hell
...the other one is we can actually on install.
How...you guys realize that it's actually impossible to build safe
...installer there's no way to do it because the?
The previous non app model will say it didn't actually
...there's no way to know whether removing a file with
safer not you say well but I put the files down of course I can take them away.
Unless someone else would...also lay down the same file and they said look,
it's already there great I don't have to put that file down and then you take it away and that
apparatus right so there's that was one of the things the there's one of the
financial companies in new york they have this policy they would never ever on
install and app they had something they called hobbling.
So, they wouldn't run your own installer but if they...if they need to get rid of and app they would public
from like what does that mean and they're like basically we render all the exes
...and just leave it there but like you sears is that we
had too many times we tried on install something took down our systems we lost money so we don't
do that anymore with that backs and with the app model we could actually safely
...stuff because what we don't allow people to do is just randomly take dependencies
on files in your app and one of the things we actually do is if you saw that big long
half the path to your app changes constantly every time you
release new version the
path changes we do that for a whole bunch of reasons internally
because it turns out when you're installing never ever edit of
file everett file we figured out some times our goes up like it
does happen some times you lose data and if the our goes out
...in middle bettering a file
user system is now in some crazy state and they have to basically they have to flatten the
machine so we never do that so because of this even if someone was really
tempted to try and go and take some crazy dependency on your files first of all
...were no be stable path for them to do and then one other thing we're actually doing is
...going to change the loader so that if someone that's not you tries to
load your files into their process will fail.
The reason we have to do this is we
...installs to be.
Reliable to not be terrible like there now and,
it turns out that if you're.
If you're app starts getting loaded into lots of other processes
guess what now is really hard to service you because someone's loaded
your dl we go and we go and installed
the new version maybe they're trying to...to talk...for some reason you change the,
you know, you change some com interface everything blows up
user gets angry so we just don't let it happen so, this is the, you know,
the wonderful lies that we tell you or tell your code is this nice merging.
Next thing we do is what happens when.
Area what happens when you write something to the system
...first of all if you're writing to the registry we
...you say I'm going to write to each case...blah-blah-blah we say
...you totally did a good job we right over here?
So, that way when we go to...install you we
...just rip it out and we don't have to worry about the fact that like hey I wonder if I wonder if other people
are taking dependencies on the crazy thing that you put into the registry which does mean if you
went road software that try to use the registry to talk to some other piece of software from some
other company we just broke you...so who so happy that we broke you because
...terrible when it comes to the file system basically the only thing we
...is that data write the app data folders just that it's
...app data users aren't supposed to go in
poking around there looking at stuff we hide it we market all kinds of ways that users
on see it that's like your personal little scratch space well,
we just re-direct that so if you're apps...case...blah-blah-blah app data
...yup you totally...looks your code looks like it wrote there just redirected somewhere else
and one really nice side effect about that as a few minutes going to talk about you know,
building new features we put it in the same app data directory where
all other universal apps get their app data put in so it actually
starts future...it starts it starts like automatically moving your code forward to use the
right model without you even doing anything at the same time you don't like being lied to you can just right
there directly you don't have to let us lied to you can actually just go to the right thing?
So, that's how that works a little bit about full trust activation
...how many people actually even heard the term app container.
A few view when you
build universal app it runs in app container it's basically a sandbox we lock
your code way and then we give you access to the system that for to
things of user would want your apt access and we don't just give you carte launch to do
And, this has been a huge success for us because those apps that people get from the
store I know...everything's twice I...install hey that's great I'll use it
is not-so-great...install it because it really can't do any damage.
These apps who we're going to run full trust and full
trust is outside of the app container full trust means you're running
as the actual user so because of this like.
Please be careful right it's, you know, a lot of people
think well hey it's great I got to do everything it's like the really bad part about it as you can do everything.
Ever have a bug...bug forever bug your code yet have a bug
and someone exploits it you just totally...user like I don't know about you
but I actually don't want that like that's great our yea but I don't want to you know,
I don't want that responsibility I have my app I have the data that I
access that's all I really want to...access to well that's not the way the non
that model worked so we're going to continue to run your stuff full trust so that
...can work but we hope and we will help you over time start
migrating your code to the app container so that you can eventually,
you know, be protect the user...and have a much more secure model so,
the things right...in vone that were targeting right now like I tap
on the tile your app kind of like...did with photoshop elements your
app launches that's all that's running full trust...happy you register file type
associations are custom your eyes schemes or something great
well-run that code full trust other than that if you want to do other things like,
for example,
had someone say hey can I build one of those I, you know, I saw in the keynote that app to have contract thing
...apps can call-in to me and like I can provide data back in the band stuff and,
the answer's,
yeah, you can and when you write that code you're going to write universal windows
at code that runs in the app container so but,
at the same time the big question is
okay but what if the thing I'm doing actually it's my other is my older
when thirty-two or dot net code and the answer is we're going to
let you activate... you're going to have some code were in that scenario running in the app container
have some running full trust will give you a communication...to talk to each other and
let-you activate each other so if someone calls your app
contract and, your full trust code...running at will give you the ability to launch it if
...full trust codes running and you want to called on interrupt container code we'll let you do that we'll give you
an efficient communication channel for that?
And, the reason that we're doing this is because.
Overall we think most people actually in the feedback we've gotten as most people actually want to
be a real universal windows app that are run anywhere.
Right like how many you guys will be called run xbox running hollow
...running all these cooler devices as long as you have that full trust code you won't run
on those devices because those
devices only use the pure universal windows at model.
...only...app container the only call those set...sets of api is that are supported for that so,
most people actually want to get...it's just it's just it's a historical artifact their code
is the way it is you wrote the code that we told you...right to do what you wanted to do
so...know that people want to get there so the very first thing that
we did was say hey the moment that you run that conversion process
your universal windows...which means you can do anything that universal windows
...seriously anything because.
Why not you are universals...you want you want to basically
...contract go in...app contract you want to be you know, a picker target you want to be a
shared target whatever the stuff you want to do you can do that so,
I'm going to try to get to the question soon so,
basically...the process that you'll go through if you actually really want to get
to universal is that you don't by the way that's fine you can keep running the project see but,
we internally have been doing this we've got a lot of experience with that so,
for example, I don't know if you guys been playing
with windows insider builds but if you have you'll notice that the start menu like parts of the shell of
the action center all those things those are actually uw ways they?
Run...app container and how did we get there well we started with we
have full trust code?
That was like,
you know, not nfc but the, you know, our internal equivalent of nfc totally awesome and,
the very first thing that everyone does is they do...on they put
...right so they basically so all these teams as a great we want we want
to new really modern feeling ui so they go and build.
And, they look at all the stuff that they can do in the app container they just continue to pull
out stuff n at first not everything can work just because a bunch of its old code
...did other stuff so they leave that code full trust and they just they basically
talked to it they have a little piped to it so, you know, and, then over time more
of those things they keep moving into their app overtime luckily the cool thing is the
app works the whole time right so you have a working...
...slowly make changes that whatever paces
right fear business and then a certain point.
You don't have any more full trust code left you're done and once you're done there now you can go...you can run
...xbox can run on, you know, phony koran anywhere you want.
And, that isyou know, that's our main goal for this project beside, you know,
yes, we you want...we want traps in the store but we really want
your code bases to live on for a long-time.
Other things that we're doing is back in when
...we have this we have this rule were basically snot rule but
...was like a guideline we said okay we're...build all these new great api...are much easier to use
...thirty-two like call us within old pointer and will fail and then we'll tell you the
...like we most people hated those patterns so we gave them all-new
aps...we did this thing where we said well if we have a new one then we won't
bring the old one forward into the into the development platform for
...you know, universal laps so there are things like hey I have tons of when
...code we said I see we are...sockets are much easier use those?
Are like well?
But, I already have code it's really easy because they're already works that's already been
the bugs so I think using that's easier so one changes we've made
in windows ten is we're bringing a ton of those things back so things like
...create thread all those things I guess we have an awesome
...pool but if you already have create third code disco...and those things
will be available inside the app container inside sdk that will just pass the regular whack.
So, actually moving all that code in
...container gets much easier the big things that you'll do or things like
well I used to use the that olds like file open picker
well change the code to use the new one the new one has a ton more features that
...lone does and sport like picking from other apps and stuff you make a few changes like that
...our...been it's actually been quite easy to make the move much easier than we thought I really
should have...people because I was trying to say...going to be easy and...told me it's...be hard.
I was right they were wrong.
All right so ...we should get to the questions like here's the summary right so project seizure bridge
from...ways to uw is that right good ans will convert, you
know, and,...well why do you and you can start using
the wa features so fifty-minute perfect questions.
...sorry so there's...here I it'd be it'd be more convenient to get to the
...because then I have to do less work by not repeating a question I'm lazy...a
ogg developers are so this is cool and I work in the industrial space
yep and most of our customers don't have access to the windows store so we can we convert
...at code...still just install without...absolutely, yeah,
there's, there's like getting into the store is nice and if you don't want to
adult yes you still uses this is just part of the platform like that app that
I that I did I just did...fx package so the rules for
project see apps or the same is for all the other apps right and I
...if you've seen in the scene and some of the other demos and stuff where now we have a page you
want to side load apps you flip a switch that switch affects project see exactly the same
...it does for all other affects.
...side-to-side so how does this work between single user multi-user apps
...obvious certain apps are...multiple users on a system.
Well, so, ...like it works the same way that the does for other app
...apps which is, you know, it's the installation is per
user meaning that like if you and I are both running on the same machine and you install
and app I don't see it unless I also install it under the covers there's
still only one copy of the app we have a single instance store and everything and, when you're...gets run it
runs that user if you're on a terminal server there's a hundred a hundred users and they all
launch the app there's a hundred instances of the app one
...each session...reading the data to the user directory then is that than roamed like
...like universal app on one driving all that so it goes
machine to machine well so what we did is because the
...model worlds like didn't actually do roaming we had that roaming directorate after
...data I'm going-to by the way after this talk I'm also going to be...hour and a half thing out and
experts section or whatever it's called was...
Insider...I'm...the entire...after this
and we can have a longer talk about like what was wrong with that but all that stuff we put in the
non rooming section but your app has a
roman directory as well and you can call those api is...you can start with
the moment you do the conversion you start running you can...put stuff in the rowing directory and you will...
Just to clarify the registry step the hp, you know,
current user stuff with that automatically...then no
of it won't know...because actually most apps can't handle that anyway.
...things like so automatically set up some shares or...he's big guys are ...said
...does things like automatically setting up some...shares or connecting to
a certain wireless networks on...is that going to be stuff we could do with this and
if not is their way...easily suppressing the apps...those kinds of things don't show up well,
at runtime your app can do whatever it would normally
do unless it was doing it by like going through you ac...run admin so, yeah,
you can still do all the say all the same stuff that you would normally do the biggest thing is if you're
if what...doing was going and editing the registry to change the way the os works nope but,
other than that, yeah, and, if we do usc things what does that look like if we try to do not
...fail okay, yeah, we're just going to be like we're just going to block
...because users like we're like the whole promise of this is you're not going to
regret at the moment you start going road and running a system and doing fun stuff I
...have the best of intentions but you might mess up their machine okay thanks.
Okay, so, what about things that were previously disallow out from store apps,
for example, accessing custom hardware using I october
...or doing ipc like using
named types or things like that well that still work yep that'll all continue
to work because you are just your app is still does running I mean really mostly what
we did was just change the underlying installation deployment management stuff
...code still running you can continue to do whatever you did before so I can use calm and
...mine all those things as well yes commenting my all that stuff work but,
the...the big the big like no,
is where like if you did something that cause some like other app to load your binary
is into that app or something like were blocking that for now we do what by the
way we do believe deeply in extensibility we believe deeply in
plugins and all those things are built we're currently working...all details now
...we are working on a model to have a nice clean plug-in model but,
that probably won't be part of eone but, yeah, other than that you're just you're code
...and how does the desktop activity modulate or how does that affect this
sorry...the desktop activity moderator...to connected standby
...how does that affect these type of applications...the same as if you...with...
So, but, you said that there are apps like there's a portion of the applicant do the same thing as
all wyatt any of the stuff that you do that that's like so flushes take,
for example, you say hey background triggers but, yeah,
I want...background triggers of those all will work like as member the everything,
everything seriously thing true yes you can do all those things that code
will run in the app container and that code will be subject appeal
m as always but yes you can do all those and can call into the
code that's suspended by the this of activity moderator well actually the way that the way that
...am works is when we wake up the system?
We actually do wake those processes for brief period of time so
yes it actually will work we...the original the original design of it we
didn't and it turned out that not everything worked out so great so we had a changes so our app uses something
called code meter that's meant to basically encrypt the binary...keep them tamper
resistant...us ducks net type of almanac is
this provide some of that same type of functionality, yeah.
The same way so,
what we do for all of the binary...deployed throughout backs is first of all as they come
down we have like everything's digitally signed we have all of the we have all the
checks sounds as every block comes off the network we check if it's been tampered with
roadway once it gets on-disk we lock it down with a whole bunch of different things we have
we have some...secret stuff that we do we change the colonel
in the file system we have things we have a thing called a super...like, you know, so, you can't just go and
...going-to-take privilege and just take over and do stuff all of that also applies
one other cool thing you can do at any moment your code can we have an api
zing call say tell me that files been tempered with?
Goal re-check it right now and tell me
if it's still passes the digital signature check so yes so
you get all of that for free as part of the conversion...and second so
we'll visual studio twenty fifteen the full version use this app
Formally enough...I've the it was it was support...for years like
lots of customers doing it and we met we talked to that group many times and we
had never done it and then they saw the keynote and I immediately got an email so don't
know but at least I can tell you people are interested now...my app...one...what would be
...to bring...would still go and run it through the converter you would do the click
once thing whatever but, I can say right now I know we've tried we've tried
that the past and we...working but we haven't tested that with project see yet but,
yeah, we you basically go through the same process but from that point
forward you wouldn't be a click once app anymore right
...and all the servicing we're now just come through the app...deployment stack.
...as a going to ask conses well what about some...features of click once like
h optional download groups and stuff will be the support for this kind of things in
rsa optional member groups optional download groups of optional download groups,
you know,...so, we're not we're not doing anything like we're not taking any of the click
...technology but at the same time we are doing things like
we're working on and
it's not it's not there yet we already know we've got lots of request just even for universal
apps to say I want to have downloadable content where and we know
how-to-do-it because if you actually look at app...we actually have a single map x bundle it's made up a bunch of
app xfiles and we already do things like automatically do language
...and everything so we are planning on extending it
to that but we will not be doing it the way that click ones doing it will be doing at the...
What about merge modules where we have a shared merge module between
two different applications that gets installed its own directory right now,
yeah, so, well, first of all two things merge modules are evil?
And, but, we do is way better which is under the covers what I talked about that
like differing we'll just...up for between two versions of your app we dipper differ
cross everything so if you have ten different like apps that all have the same
dls like, for example,
sq lights really popular write-in sq light ships aversion that
supports universal apps like you have a hundred apps are all using sq light there's
one copy on-disk there's one there's one dl on-disk you get all the same benefits you
get had you actually use emerge module and try to stuff the same things and into the same actual directory
...do...convert when we do the conversion do we just let the merge module install and
...just figured out and then we install the other app it'll just...it's there and, yeah, exactly,
yeah, you do nothing you just run we'll run the conversion twice let those evil merge
models do whatever stuff that they did don't worry about it and,
the deployment stack takes care of everything automatically.
So, it sounds like project see protects against accidental you know,
problems with the systemis it also security moreover no so we will
then be store apps that-you nowcan't really necessarily trust
apps from the store if there project see apps because...full trust,
yeah, so, this one thing we talked about
im by the way I don't work on the store I don't know what store policies are going to be
in place I don't know what the on boarding is going to look like or whatever but,
yeah, we definitely know that is absolutely a concern and we are ballot we've been balancing the two
like early on we aired on the side of we're not going to do it because it might potentially but we
also trust you guys so we're going to put some trust and you can sort of and,
you know, but, there will be checks and balances I mean luckily because it's coming through the app
...stack if we have to we still have like
kill but mechanisms and stuff like that so if something militias does make it into the store and
does start harming our users we can turn it off which I hope that doesn't happen often
...so that would include like if I process dot start something and,
you know, it would go around perhaps go around the redirects and stuff yeah, absolutely I mean
if you're evil then you'll be able to get around the stuff I'm not
...by the way you're not personally...but, yeah, that I mean, you know,
is one of those things that if we find people coloring outside the lines like we have the rails
there so for people who mean well like we help them do the right thing without even changing your
code which I think it's pretty neat other than that like we're just going to have to keep an eye out but, you know,
we always have the anytime you deploy software, you know,
even in the browser like there's always that problem so, you know,
all the all the or other mitigation that we have for this stuff will continue to use so I'm still trying to get my head
...this full trust and
...container stuff okay and when
...native code call-in to the universal windows platform to use
though you cplus-plus cx or is this some sort of replacement for that I'm not sure I
understand the question so...so-if let me just let me try to explain
quickly as I can so you have your full trust code running right and you can have in
you can activate the code in the app container either through some background task or we will give you
a called...just say hey run my code okay so you'll have that and then what
...just give you is we're like we will give you a pipe to communicate now
your question might be what is the pipe look like and is it...like is ad
...as...this is that where still actually we're still obsessing that out we've done a
couple we've been we've been playing with it and we've been doing a few different ones it turns out that?
...com can be somewhat tricky.
We'll say especially if you have to processes one of which can be suspended
...one of which is going to be suspended so we carly been thinking about actually using
the apt app model that we have to go-between apps are now were you basically pass value sets
there which is kind of like moral it's basically a glorified jason document and,
just passing that back and forth so we played around with that sum and it's actually quite promising so my guess is
we'll probably look something like that I have...more question
...I'm going to apologize for the...with active-x and it's called.
And, in the past we had the option to put on manifest the registry so I
don't need to actually I can run like a portable application...the average regarded.
So, yeah, so, right now what we do manifests right and that manifest could
even go to the to the resources of this equitable so it's...get don't know-how
this process will be able to get it also right now...like so the active-x
was bunch of different things one of it was like a deployment technology not doing that right so
you can do that but if you had active-x control you...using it in your app that like
that'll continue to work whether you were using registry...or you are using regular
calm those are both work so, I think you'll be fine but if you're talking about that other part which is
the pt part no like you wouldn't be able to say hey I'm going to take the active-x
...up on a website and just have...automatically update itself that wouldn't.
All right I think does that...
...so but I'm going to but if you still have questions
we're just going over to the what's called insider lounge around the corner...another hour and a half.